Sofia Dutta

Software Engineer

८ (443) 554-4170 **≥** sofia.dutta17@gmail.com

in https://linkedin.com/in/sofiadutta ## https://sofiadutta.github.io

Software Engineer with over a decade of experience working with large quantities of data. Worked on every aspect of the software development life cycle, from design & development of core functionality to production deployments in cloud environments. Seeking software engineering opportunities in the US.

SKILLS

Programming – Python, Java, SQL, PL/SQL

Data Science – Apache PySpark, Looker, LookML, PyTorch, Sci-kit Learn, Tensorflow, Hadoop Data/Software Engineering – Apache Airflow, Databricks, Jupyter Notebook, Google Colab, Git Cloud – Google Cloud Platform, Google Compute Engine, Google Cloud Storage, Google Cloud SQL, AWS S3 Back-end – Google BigQuery Table, Oracle Databases, PostgreSQL, MySQL, MongoDB, JSON Domain knowledge – Big Data Analytics, Deep Learning, Machine Learning

WORK EXPERIENCE

Technical Leader @ NewWave Telecom & Technologies, Inc., Windsor Mill, MD, USA

Jan 2021 – Present

- Designed the system architecture, database schema, and data workflow for the Imersis data quality analytics
- Built the project's cloud infrastructure setup and processed hundreds of millions of healthcare records using Apache PySpark to compute data quality metrics.
- Created Looker dashboard visualizations with drill-down options that "explains" why the data quality came out to a certain value.
- Due to the lack of large quantities of data, re-designed the machine learning goal of the project into a data quality "Explainable AI" system.
- Built a data quality system that allows clients to understand how to improve their data quality over time.
- Using a four-fold workflow automation strategy saved tens of thousands of dollars in cloud costs for the project.

Data Science Intern @ NewWave Telecom & Technologies, Inc., Windsor Mill, MD, USA

May 2020 - Dec 2020

- Helped speed up the project's data processing pipeline 10-fold by moving to Google Cloud Platform (GCP).
- Managed DevOps on GCP and connected the cloud infrastructure to back-end Big Data tables for delivering results to dashboards.

Software Engineer @ Tata Consultancy Services, Kolkata, India

Nov 2006 – Feb 2018

- Led the design, development, and delivery of API interfaces using PL/SQL stored procedures for several projects of TCS.
- Carried out change-based regression impact analysis, created software functional specifications, and prepared test plans for several projects of TCS.
- Performed system integration, user acceptance, and performance testing and ensured client systems had very high uptime even when carrying out data migration activities.
- Saved millions of dollars in potential revenue lost to the client and was awarded for the said effort by clients.

EDUCATION

Udacity Nanodegree: Deep Learning

Masters in Data Science from the University of Maryland, Baltimore County, Baltimore, MD Bachelor's in Computer Science from West Bengal University of Technology, Kolkata, India

Oct 2021

Jan 2019 – Dec 2020

Jun 2006 - Nov 2010